Aline and Eero Saarinen
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Aline and Eero Saarinen Personal Papers, 1928-1977, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-4, 15, OV 16; 3.7 linear feet)
  - Photographs, 1940s-1970, 1.4:
    Photographs of Aline Saarinen consist of ones of her as young girl; ones of her graduating from Vassar College in 1935; ones of her as a Red Cross worker during the Second World War; ones of her as an art critic in the 1950s and as a television correspondent in the 1960s; ones of her serving as the representative of the President at the Inauguration of the Venezuelan President, Raul Leoni, in 1964; and ones of her receiving various honorary degrees.
    Photographs of family members include ones of Aline's mother, father, and brother, and her sons, Donald and Hal Louchheim, and their families; ones of her son with Eero, Eames; ones of Eero with his first wife, Lily Swann Saarinen, and their children; and ones of Aline and Eero with their children, including ones from a trip to Hvittrask, Finland in 1958.
    Photographs from various trips include ones of Aline's trip to Hearst Castle in San Simeon, CA, and ones of a trip to Greece with her and Eero (which are of particular note because the pictures were taken by Eero and feature examples of Greek architecture). Other photographs include ones of various designs by Eero, ones of the sketches of the winning design for the Sydney Opera House, and miscellaneous and unidentified ones.
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen as a Young Girl, 1910s-1920s (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen, Graduation from Vassar College, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen, 1940s, (See also Box 15) (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen, 1950s, (3 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen, 1960s, (3 folders; see also Box 15; not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen, Inauguration of Venezuelan President Raul Leoni, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Other Photographs of Inauguration of Venezuelan President Raul Leoni, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen Receiving Honorary Degrees, 1964, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen and William Hewitt, Deere Company (Moline, IL), 1960s (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Photographs of Eero Saarinen, 1950s-1961, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
    - Photographs of Aline and Eero Saarinen, 1954-1957 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Photographs of Family (Box 3)
      - The Bernstein Family, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Donald and Hal Louchheim, 1940s-1960s, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
      - Eero Saarinen, Lily Swann Saarinen and Children, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Aline and Eero Saarinen and Children, mid 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Aline and Eero Saarinen and Children in Hvittrask, Finland, 1958, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Eames Saarinen, 1955-1965, (3 folders; see also Box 15) (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
      - Louchheim Grandchildren, 1963-1970, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 33-35)
      - Charles Alan, 1967, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Luna L. Davis (Photographer: Berenice Abbott), undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Photographs of Louchheim Family and House in Stamford, CT, circa 1948 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Photographs from Aline Saarinen's Trip to Hearst Castle (San Simeon, CA), 1958 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Photographs of Trip to Greece Taken by Eero Saarinen, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Photographs of Unidentified Party (Aline and Eero Saarinen and Children in attendance), 1950s (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Photographs of Unidentified House, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Photographs of House on St. Roman's Terrace, New Haven, CT, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Photographs of Eero Saarinen Designs, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Photographs of Sketches of Winning Design for Sydney Opera House, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Miscellaneous and Unidentified Photographs, 1956-1963, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 46-47)
    - Slides, (Not scanned) (Box 4)
      - Trip to Europe (Lily Swann Saarinen and Children), 1950s (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Ray [Eames?], 1950s (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Sampe, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Eames Saarinen, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Hvittrask, Finland, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Aline Saarinen, circa 1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Art Slides, undated, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Art Slides (lantern glass slides), undated, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Art Slides (35mm glass slides), undated, (See slide boxes) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - UNESCO Architecture (?) Slides (35mm glass slides), undated, (See slide boxes) (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Architecture and Design Slides, undated, (See slide boxes) (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous Slides, undated, (See slide boxes) (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Oversize, Photographs of Aline Saarinen, 1940s, (See Box 3, F9) (Box 15 (sol))
    - Oversize, Photographs of Aline Saarinen, 1960s, (See Box 3, F13-15) (Box 15 (sol))
    - Oversize, Photographs of Family, Eames Saarinen, 1955-1965, (See Box 3, F30-32) (Box 15 (sol))
- Aline Saarinen Professional Papers, 1906-1969, Series 2:; (Boxes 4-14, 15, OV 16; 9.8 linear) feet)
  Series consists of files stemming from Aline Saarinen's professional activities as an art critic, author, and television correspondent, and as a member of arts-related and other committees.
  The Aline Saarinen Professional Papers series is arranged into six subseries:
  2.1: Writings, 1933-1967
  2.2: Research Material for The Proud Possessors, 1906-1967 (bulk 1956-1959)
  2.3: Research Material on Stanford White, 1880s-1969
  2.4: NBC Correspondent Files, 1961-1971
  2.5: Miscellaneous Research Files, circa 1960-1964, undated
  2.6: Committee Files, 1961-1968
  - Writings, 1933-1967, 2.1:
    Subseries consists of manuscripts, typescripts, notes, notecards and clippings of Aline Saarinen's writings. Her writings include: articles on art and architecture for The New York Times and other publications, including a manuscript of her article on Eero Saarinen with his annotations in the margins and her notebook from her interview with him; samples of her early art criticism and early writings, including some short stories and college essays; lectures and speeches on art, architecture and related topics, including ones on Eero Saarinen, art collectors and collecting, modern art, culture and visual arts, and writing biography; scripts for television shows; notes on project ideas and plans developed and presumably shared with her literary agent, Bernice Cozzens; and other creative writing such as fiction, a play, and poems (some of which may have been written by her and others of which may have been transcribed by her) and personal writing such as a piece on the suicide of woman she knew in passing, Ruth Gornick.
    Writings are arranged alphabetically by type.
    - Article for Harper's Magazine, "Uncle Sam as an Art Expert," 1954 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Articles on Architecture, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Articles on Architecture - Clippings, 1950, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Article on Art, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Articles on Art - Clippings, 1949-1963, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
    - Articles on Art for McCall's, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Article on Eero Saarinen, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Article on Eero Saarinen - Notebook, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Articles and Stories, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Articles, Miscellaneous - Clippings, 1947, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Early Art Criticism - Clippings, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Early Writings, 1933-1935, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 27-29)
    - Fiction, Miscellaneous, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Lecture, "Art Collecting in America", circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Lecture on "Style", Vassar College, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Lectures and Speeches, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Lectures and Speeches, Notecards, 1950s-1960s, (12 folders) (Box 5, Folder 7-18)
    - Play, "The Correct Collections", 1952 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Poetry (by Aline Saarinen and others?), 1962 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Project Ideas and Plans, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Television Script, "The American Image" (written by Aline Saarinen and John Lord), undated, (Not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Television Script, "Venus in Venice", 1964, (Not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Television Scripts, Miscellaneous, 1960s, (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 24-26)
    - Writing on Ruth Gornick's Suicide, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Research Material for The Proud Possessors, 1906-1967 (bulk 1956-1959), 2.2:
    Series consists of files stemming from Aline Saarinen's work researching and writing her book, The Proud Possessors, which was published by Random House in 1958. Files consist of notes, manuscripts, correspondence, photographs and printed material on art collectors, as well the application for a Guggenheim grant (which was awarded to Saarinen in 1957), Eero Saarinen's notes on the book, a scrapbook of correspondence received in response to the publication of the book (of particular note is Peggy Guggenheim's negative response to the chapter on her), and clippings of reviews and other articles about the book after its publication. Among the correspondents are Bernard Berenson, Dorothy Miller, Bernice Cozzens, Albert Ten Eyck Gardner, Alfred H. Barr (?), Edward Steichen, Francis Brown, Hiram Haydn, Daniel Cotton Rich, John Goldsmith Phillips, George Heard Hamilton, Dorothy Sieberling, Saul Steinberg, Sam N. Behrman, Jean Lipman, Irving Hoffman, Electra Webb, Henry Allen Moe, Peggy Guggenheim, Alice B. Toklas, H. P. Roche, Cy Sulzberger, Clifford Odets, and Alfred A. Knopf.
    The material on John Quinn includes correspondence between Saarinen and Jeanne Foster Roberts; letters to Foster from Quinn and his sister, Julia Anderson; a copy of a letter to Foster from William Butler Yeats and a drawing of Quinn possibly by Yeats; material relating to Roger Casement, Foster, and Florence Farr; and photographs of Quinn and Foster, and Quinn with Constantin Brancusi, Picasso and Mme Picasso, Henri Pierre Roche and Erik Satie.
    The material on Edward Root includes correspondence between Root and his father, Elihu, dating from 1903 to 1936; letters to Root from Charles Culver, Robert de Forest, Frederick James Gregg, Ernest Lawson, George Luks, Duncan Phillips, and Grace Root, dating from 1909 to 1936; and copies of two letters to Edward Christiana, dated 1949.
    Files are typically arranged according to format and then alphabetically according to name of collector.
    - Guggenheim Grant, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1958, (3 folders) (Box 6, Folder 3-5)
    - Scrapbook of Correspondence, 1958-1959, (5 folders) (Box 6, Folder 6-10)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Berenson, Bernard (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, 1953, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence, 1957, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 15-16)
      - Correspondence, 1958, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 17-18)
      - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Aline Saarinen Writings, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - Printed Material, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Collector Files (Box 6)
      - Cone, Claribel and Etta, 1949-1956, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Freer, Charles Lang, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - Gardner, Isabella Stewart, 1957-1959 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - Gilcrease, Thomas, 1948-1958, (2 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 6, Folder 26-27)
      - Guggenheim, Peggy, 1949, 1956-1958, (2 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 6, Folder 28-29)
      - The Havemeyers, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 30)
      - Hirshhorn, Joseph H., 1956-1958, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 6, Folder 31)
      - Ingersoll, R. Sturgis and Johnson, John G., 1939-1958, (5 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 6, Folder 32-36)
      - Morgan, J. Pierpont, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      - Quinn, John, 1956-1962, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 38-41)
      - Quinn, John - Miscellaneous Original Papers, 1918-1927, undated (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Quinn, John - Material Relating to Roger Casement, 1959, undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Quinn, John - Material on Jeanne Robert Foster, 1959, undated (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Quinn, John - Material Relating to Florence Farr, 1906 (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - The Rockefellers, 1928, 1955-1958, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 46-47)
      - Root, Edward Wales, 1956-1958, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 48-49)
      - Root, Edward Wales - Original Correspondence, 1903-1949 (Box 6, Folder 50)
      - Root, Edward Wales - Memorial Exhibition, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 51)
      - The Steins, 1957-1959 (Box 6, Folder 52)
      - Webb, Electra Havemeyer, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 53)
      - Webb, Electra Havemeyer - Printed Material, 1953-1955, (2 folders) (Box 6, Folder 54-55)
    - Notes (Notebooks) (Box 7)
      - A-D (Altman, Barnes, Cone, and Dreier), 1955-1958 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - "Freer", 1955-1958 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - "Gardner", 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - "G-H" (Gilcrease, Guggenheim, and Hirshhorn), 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Havemeyer, 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - "I-L" (Ingersoll, Johnson, Hearst, and Lewisohn), 1955-1958 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Mellon, 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - "Morgan", 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - "Potter Palmer", 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - "Quinn", 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - R-S (Robinson, Root, and Stein), 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - "Rockefeller", 1956-1958, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
      - T-W (Thompson, Walters, and Webb), 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - "General Background", 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - "Biblio", 1956-1958 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Eero Saarinen's Notes on the Book, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, 1956-1957, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Drafts, 1957-1958, (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 19-22)
    - Photographs (Box 7)
      - Altman, Benjamin, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - Berenson, Bernard, circa 1958 (Box 7, Folder 24)
      - Cone, Claribel and Etta, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
      - Freer, Charles Lang, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
      - Gardner, Isabella Stewart, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
      - Gilcrease, Thomas, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - Guggenheim, Peggy, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Hirshhorn, Joseph H., 1950s (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - Morgan, J. Pierpont, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - Palmer, Mr. and Mrs. Potter, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
      - Quinn, John, 1918-1922, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 33-34)
    - Photographs (Box 8)
      - The Rockefeller Family, 1957, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Root, Edward Wales, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - The Stein Family, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Webb, Electra Havemeyer, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Unidentified, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Negatives, undated, (Not scanned) (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material on Collectors, 1955-1957, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Scrapbook, Clippings on The Proud Possessors, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Other Clippings on The Proud Possessors, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Book Contract for Italy, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Book Jacket, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Research Material on Stanford White, 1880s-1969, 2.3:
    Subseries consists of files stemming from Aline Saarinen's research for a planned, but never completed, biography of Stanford White "as an interpreter of the Age of Elegance." Included are: correspondence, notebooks, writings, scattered original material belonging to Bessie White, Stanford White and the firm of McKim, Mead and White, printed material, photographs, and architectural drawings.
    - Correspondence, 1959-1969, 2.3.1:
      Correspondence consists of letters exchanged with Aline Saarinen's literary agent, publisher, scholars, friends and relatives of White, and others, as well as responses to her inquiry about Stanford White published in The New York Times. Correspondence concerns book ideas, research inquiries, her struggles with the work, and related matters. Correspondents include: Bernice Cozzens, Random House, Wayne Andrews, Mrs. Lawrence Grant White (White's daughter-in-law), Welles Bosworth, R. W. G. Vail, Francis Brown, Edward Fowles, Van Wyck Brooks, and Evelyn Nesbit.
      Correspondence is typically arranged chronologically, except for the extended correspondence with her literary agent which is arranged in its own file.
      - Correspondence - Cozzens, Bernice, 1959-1962, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence, 1959, (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 13-15)
      - Correspondence, 1960, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 16-17)
      - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 18)
      - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence, 1963-1971 (Box 8, Folder 20)
      - Correspondence, undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Notebooks, circa 1959-1962, 2.3.2:
      Notebooks contain Aline Saarinen's notes on various topics related to Stanford White gathered in the course of her research. Individual notebooks were removed from their original binders at some previous point, and are arranged alphabetically according to subject.
      - "Biblio", circa 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 22)
      - Century, Metropolitan, and Other Clubs, circa 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 23)
      - "Cheney", circa 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 24)
      - "CHR" (Chronology), circa 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 25)
      - "Mackay", circa 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 26)
      - "McK., M. and W. Architecture", circa 1959-1962, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 27-28)
      - "New York", circa 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 29)
      - "Newport", circa 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 30)
      - "R. G. W." (Richard Grant White), circa 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 31)
      - "S. W. and Artists", circa 1959-1962, (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 32-33)
      - "S. W. General", circa 1959-1962, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
      - "S. W. Jobs" (Box 9)
        - A-B (Astor, Barney, Col. Day, Box Hill, and Breese), circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - "Ch-H" (Colony, Fish, Herald Building, and Houses, Miscellaneous), circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - I-M (IRT, Judson, Hyde, Knickerbocker, Madison Square, Miscellaneous, and Monuments), circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 5)
        - N-V (NYU, Oelrichs, Reid, Sherry, Tiffany, and Villard), circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 6)
        - "W-Z" (University of Virginia, Washington Arch, Payne Whitney, and William C. Whitney), circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 7)
      - "S. W. Murder", circa 1959-1962, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
      - "Unsorted", circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Miscellaneous, circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Writings, 1959-1960s, 2.3.3:
      Writings include drafts and manuscripts of chapters for Saarinen's planned biography on White and her article on White for Life Magazine. Also found are scattered research notes, an outline of the planned biography, and various writings on White and architecture by others.
      - Research Notes, circa 1959, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
      - Research Notes, "State of Buildings", 1961 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Tentative Chapter Headings and Outline, 1960, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
      - Notes and Writings, circa 1959-1962, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 17-18)
      - Drafts (Box 9)
        - "Prologue - in work (Also Prince Henry Version)", circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 19)
        - "Chapter I in work", circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 20)
        - "Chapter II in work", circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 21)
        - "Chapter III in opera", circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 22)
        - "Chapter IV - in opera", circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 23)
        - "Chapter V - in opera", circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 24)
        - "Chapter VI in opera", circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 25)
        - Chapters VII and VIII, circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 26)
        - Chapter XII (Cheneys), circa 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 27)
        - Miscellaneous, circa 1959-1962, (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 28-29)
      - Manuscripts (Box 9)
        - Article for Life, 1960s, (3 folders) (Box 9, Folder 30-32)
        - Book, Chapter I (?), 1960s (Box 9, Folder 33)
        - Book, Chapter on Richard Grant White, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 34)
        - Book, Chapter II, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 35)
        - Book, Chapter III, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 36)
        - Book, Chapter IV, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 37)
        - Book, Chapter V, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 38)
      - Manuscripts (Box 10)
        - Book, Chapter VI, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 1)
        - Book, Chapter VII, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 2)
        - Book, Chapter, VIII, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - Book, Chapter IX, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 4)
        - Book, Chapter XII (Cheneys), 1960s (Box 10, Folder 5)
        - Book, Chapter XIV (Katherine Mackay), 1960s (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Miscellaneous, 1960s, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
      - Caption Suggestions, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Writings by Others, 1962, undated, (2 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
    - Original Material, 1880s-1936, 1960, 2.3.4:
      Original material includes certain scattered papers of Bessie White and Stanford White, and scattered office "files" of the architectural firm McKim, Mead and White, which were presumably accumulated by Aline Saarinen in the course of her research. Also found is a microfilm reel of the correspondence of Richard Grant White (approximately 25 letters) and Stanford White (1 letter) held by the Huntington Art Library.
      The papers belonging to Bessie White consist of correspondence from her father-in-law, Richard Grant White; scrapbooks on the Washington Centennial and White's Washington Art, and on the Thaw Murder Trial; and written reminiscences of White. The papers belonging to Stanford White consist of lists, notes, and other documents. The McKim, Mead and White documents include memoranda and correspondence; files consisting of correspondence, contracts estimates, and descriptions for various projects (extensive documentation for the Whitelaw Reid residence can be found); and a record book.
      - Bessie White Papers (Box 10)
        - Correspondence, 1880s (Box 10, Folder 12)
        - Scrapbook on Washington Centennial and Arch, 1889 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        - Scrapbook, "Thaw Trial Clippings", 1907-1908, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 14-15)
        - Written Memories, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - Stanford White Papers (Box 10)
        - Menu for Dinner Honoring Stanford White, 1884 (Box 10, Folder 17)
        - Lists of Works (White's own?), undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
        - "Goods Held in Trust for Stanford White, Esq." (list with drawings), 1902 (Box 10, Folder 19)
        - Notes on Furnishings (White's own?), undated (Box 10, Folder 20)
        - "S. W.'s matters, left in the hands of McKim, Mead and White", 1894 (Box 10, Folder 21)
        - Legal Document (partial), undated (Box 10, Folder 22)
      - McKim, Mead and White Documents (Box 10)
        - Memoranda, 1887-1888, undated (Box 10, Folder 23)
        - Memoranda, 1893-1897 (Box 10, Folder 24)
        - Memoranda, 1900-1903 (Box 10, Folder 25)
        - Memoranda, 1904-1905 (Box 10, Folder 26)
        - Correspondence, 1888-1904 (Box 10, Folder 27)